Guide to the Grant Maclay Papers 1868-1966
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Grant Maclay papers
1868-1966
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umotnana.edu
Mss 136
Maclay, Grant
0.75 linear feet
Grant Maclay was a Missoula, Montana, resident with an interest in Fort Missoula. The collection contains a chronology of Fort Missoula events, correspondence regarding the decommissioning of Fort Missoula, legal documents, maps, writings, and clippings concerned with Fort Missoula. In addition, there are documents pertaining to the Maclay business.
Biographical Note
The Maclay family came to Montana in 1863 and operated a general store in Virginia City, Montana. John Maclay and a partner, J. T. Murphy, opened a general store at Fort Benton, Montana. The firm became known as Murphy-Maclay and Company and operated until the death of John Maclay on January 3, 1896. Grant Maclay opened and operated a small "corner" grocery at the intersection of South Avenue and Reserve Street in Missoula, Montana. He also owned and operated a small motel across the street. Maclay took great interest in both the history and fate of Fort Missoula.
The collection contains a chronology of Fort Missoula events, correspondence regarding the decommissioning of Fort Missoula, legal documents, maps, writings, clippings and photographs of Fort Missoula and Fort Harrison. In addition, there are documents pertaining to the Maclay business.
The collection is divided into three series:
Series I: Fort Missoula History, 10 folders, 1868-1940
Series II: Fort Missoula Decommissioning, 14 folders, 1947-1963
Series III: Grant Maclay, 5 folders, 1930-1966
Series IV: Photographs, 1909-1961
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Gift of Mrs. Grant Maclay, 1987.
Photographs were separated by the original processors and moved to the archive's photo collections, where they were numbered 89-0243 through 89-0262, 89-0287 through 89-0290, and 92-0240 thru 92-0247. In 2012 these photographs were added to this finding aid and additional unprocessed photographs were described and added to the collection.
Grocery trade--Montana
Fort Missoula (Mont.)--History
Montana; Military
- Fort Missoula History, 1868-1940; Series I; 10 folders
  This series contains a chronology, reports, histories, legal documents, correspondence and clippings concerning the history of Fort Missoula and individuals stationed there.
  - Chronological extracts from the official records of Fort Missoula, Montana, from 1877 to 1903, compiled by Captain A.E. Rothermich, 1933 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Reports, 1868-1879 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Writings: history of the fort and surrounding areas, 1931-1960 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Correspondence, 1877 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Legal documents: property lines, buildings and costs, undated (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Legal documents: executive order re: Missoula National Forest, undated (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Correspondence regarding the history of Fort Missoula, 1959 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Clippings, 1916-1940 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Maps of McCauley Homestead, 1877 and Fort Missoula, 1879 (Box-folder OS 2/1)
  - Biographical information about Major McCauley, undated (Box-folder OS 2/2)
- Fort Missoula Decommissioning, 1947-1963; Series II; 14 folders
  Correspondence, legal documents, maps, and clippings concerned with or from the time surrounding the decommissioning of Fort Missoula. Much of the correspondence is with U.S. Congressman Mike Mansfield.
  - Correspondence regarding the fort, 1947-1957 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Description of buildings and costs at Fort Missoula, undated (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Legal documents: lease agreements, 1927-1947 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Legal documents: House Joint Memorial 9, Senate Bill 3003, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Notes on a tour of Fort Missoula, undated (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Clippings, 1960 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Blueprint: Fort Missoula, maintained by Camp Hanford, 1958 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Proposed plan for a shopping center, undated (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1963 (Box-folder OS 2/3)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1963 (Box-folder OS 2/3)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1963 (Box-folder OS 2/3)
- Grant Maclay, 1930-1966; Series III; 5 folders
  Contains correspondence, financial records, clippings, and an Edward Gleim Maclay biography.
  - Correspondence and writings, 1930-1966 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Financial Records, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Clippings, 1958 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Biography of Edward Gleim Maclay, undated (Box-folder OS 2/6)
  - Correspondence regarding a product idea, undated (Box-folder OS 2/7)
- Photographs, 1909-1961; Series IV; 93 Photographs
  Contains photographs mainly of Fort Missoula and military personnel as well as Fort Harrison in Helena, Montana.
  - "Hospital, needs minor repairs." Fort Missoula, Montana., August, 1957 (Photo number 89.0243)
  - "Old mule stables. Now used as Reserve warehouse. Perfect condition inside, minor repairs needed outside." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0244)
  - "Two newly repaired duplex quarters." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0245)
  - "Hospital, needs minor repairs." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0246)
  - "Water tank, adequate water for the largest military post." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0247)
  - "Officer's Row, now being used for 12 separate quarters - once used for 23 quarters. Perfect condition." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0248)
  - "The original quartermaster building of the post. Now completely repaired and used as the officer's club." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0249)
  - Commanding officers' house at left side of photo. Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0250)
  - "Fort Missoula's original stone powder magazine. It is still used for this purpose and for other storage." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0251)
  - "Old post exchange and gymnasium, perfect condition and now being used for offices." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0252)
  - "Old Commissary. Completely renovated." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0253)
  - "Completely renovated on the outside." Barracks at Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0254)
  - "Gymnasium (one of the army's largest in perfect condition)." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0255)
  - "Maximum security barracks, very minor repairs needed." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0256)
  - "Fort Missoula Cemetery containing graves of soldiers since 1878 and heroes of the Big Hole Battle." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0257)
  - Fire station at Fort Missoula, Montana., circa 1958 (Photo number 89.0258)
  - Barracks and Army Reserve vehicles at Fort Missoula, Montana., circa 1958 (Photo number 89.0259)
  - "Old headquarters building, now in poor condition." Fort Missoula, Montana., August, 1957 (Photo number 89.0260)
  - "Entering the post. This road completely repaired and reinforced last week." Fort Missoula, Montana., August, 1957 (Photo number 89.0261)
  - "Former headquarters, Montana Military District. Fine condition." Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0262)
  - Fort Missoula, Montana. Child sitting is Otto Taylor, standing is Peter Taylor., circa 1919 (Photo number 89.0287)
  - Veuve Hall, Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Photo number 89.0288)
  - Hospital Building, Fort Missoula, Montana., circa 1958 (Photo number 89.0289)
  - Detention Buildings at Fort Missoula, Montana., circa 1958 (Photo number 89.0290)
  - Buildings at Fort Missoula, Montana., undated (Photo number 92.0240)
  - Headquarters, Fort Missoula, Montana., undated (Photo number 92.0241)
  - Post Hospital, Fort Missoula, Montana., undated (Photo number 92.0242)
  - Missoula, Montana, DeLoyd Thompson in aeroplane racing with Louis Disbrow and Joe Bianchi, Montana State Fair., August, 1957 (Photo number 92.0243)
  - Airplane at Fort Missoula, newly completed officer's row in background., 1911 (Photo number 92.0244)
  - Adjutant's office, Fort Missoula, Montana., undated (Photo number 92.0245)
  - Original log Quartermaster building, Fort Missoula, Montana. Burned circa 1972., undated (Photo number 92.0246)
  - Fort Missoula, Montana, taken from old Sutler's store., 1886 (Photo number 92.0247)
  - Soldier with a horse. Description reads: Taken in Lincoln, Montana, Billy and The Boy, David E. Blankenship., August 18, 1909 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.001)
  - Group of soldiers at the Guard House at Fort Missoula, Montana. Joe Talley on the left., 1926 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.002)
  - Master Sargeant Joe Talley in front of the old Fort Missoula headquarters building next to a cannon that was part of the loot and plunder in the Army's absence during World War II and now (8/13/1961) stands at the Hell Gate Trading Post on West Broadway, Missoula, Montana., circa 1926 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.003)
  - Master Sargeant Joe W. Talley on left in front of the original laundress' quarters built in the Winter of 1887 at a cost of $450.00. Building now (8/13/1961) used for social functions and called the Officer's Club. Fort Missoula, Montana., circa 1926 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.004)
  - Members of Company A, 4th Infantry, Fort Missoula, Montana. Vet Reed, second from left, back row., Summer 1928 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.005)
  - Guard House at Fort Missoula, Montana, after a snow storm. Photograph by Vet Reed., circa 1929-30 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.006)
  - Officers at Fort Missoula, Montana in front of the Headquarters building., 1930 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.007)
  - Trees along the main entrance road to Fort Missoula. Water was turned on for the first time in many years by Sargeant Hill. Hydrants had been mangled by farmers who used the land during the war surplus days and farmed too close to the trees., 1957 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.008)
  - Sargeant Johnnie V. Hill stationed at Fort Missoula, Montana, during Colonel McManaway's assignment. He was of much help to the community with the post fire truck and helped in the renovation of Fort Missoula., 1957 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.009)
  - Old non-commissioned officers quarters now in poor condition. The right side of these quarters were occupied by the Taylor family. John Taylor served at Fort Missoula 42 years., August 1957 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.010)
  - Ditches after first irrigation along the main Fort entrance road. Fort Missoula, Montana. The Maclay Market can be seen in the distance., August 1957 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.011)
  - Montana National Guard Offices at Fort Missoula., April 27, 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.012)
  - National Guard Garage at Fort Missoula, April 27, 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.013)
  - Main Gate on South Avenue and Reserve, water tower in the background, undated (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.014)
  - Trees along the main fort entrance road after one year of irrigation and being pruned. Fort Missoula, Montana., August 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.015)
  - National Guard armory at Fort Missoula, Montana., April 27, 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.016)
  - Colonel and Mrs. McManaway leaving the post for new assignment. This is the end of Montana Headquarters with Fort Yanton, Washington being set up as Consolidated Headquarters for the states of Montana, Oregon, Utah, Idaho and Washington. This could also well be the end of Fort Missoula., May 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.017)
  - Roy Dickerman and Dinky. We were checking the water as it neared Fort Missoula after leaving Missoula County's part of the road. (Note Colonel McManaway had the trees pruned and ditches installed for us.), Summer 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.018)
  - Peter Moret, the "Mayor" of Green Acres. Pete sold the soldiers moonshine and after prohibition built the White House Tavern which was one of the main hangouts for soldiers. Fort Missoula, Montana., 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.019)
  - Pete Moret on his porch. Missoula, Montana., undated (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.020)
  - White House Tavern next door to Pete Moret's house. During recent years the business has been leased to others for operation. Located near Fort Missoula, Montana., 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.021)
  - Company I, Fort Missoula, Montana. Lined up in front of a building., undated (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.022)
  - Targets up at the shooting range., undated (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.023)
  - Photographic portrait of Major Michael McCauley, undated (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.024)
  - Soldiers at the shooting range. Standing: Farrow; sitting: Carlson; firing, left to right: Jones, Wilson, Hammer, Hoephler, Dever., undated (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.025)
  - XXI Corps Headquarters Building. General Frank Milburn, football coach, West Point, 1926-1930; Douglas Fesseuden, football coach, University of Illinois, 1935-1941 and 1946-1948; Harry Adams, assistant football coach, The University of Montana, 1921-1953, except war period., undated (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.026)
  - Wide angle view of Fort Missoula and the surrounding area. Missoula, Montana., undated (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.027)
  - Rundown buildings and overgrown landscape. Hospital at Fort Missoula, Montana. Same as negative #89.0243., 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.028)
  - Housing at Fort Missoula, Montana. Officer's Row. Same as negative #89.0248., 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.029)
  - Single story buildings with tall smoke stacks at Fort Missoula, Montana. Maximum security barracks. Same as negative #89.0256., 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.030)
  - Large, two story, brick building. Gymnasium at Fort Missoula, Montana. Same as negative #89.0255., 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.031)
  - Duplex housing at Fort Missoula, Montana. Same as negative #89.0245., 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.032)
  - Long flat detention buildings at Fort Missoula, Montana. Same as negative #89.0290., 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.033)
  - Old mule stables. Large concrete building at Fort Missoula, Montana. Same as negative #89.0244., 1958 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.034)
  - Army National Guard garage at Fort Missoula, Montana., undated (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.035)
  - Housing at Fort Harrison, Helena, Montana., undated (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.036)
  - Soldiers in formation and large buildings at Fort Harrison, Helena, Montana., 1909 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.037)
  - Very large brick building at Fort Harrison, Helena, Montana., 1909 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.038)
  - Man in uniform standing in a field, possibly the shooting range, at Fort Harrison, Helena, Montana., 1909 (Box-folder 1/23, Photo number 136.039)
  - Group of 22 unidentified photographs of buildings, people and various scenes at Fort Missoula and Fort Harrison in Helena, Montana. Also included is an early map of the Fort Missoula Military Reservation., undated (Box-folder 1/23)